Pankaj Malhotra

PERSONAL DATA

PHONE: +1-206-396-2981

EMAIL: malhotrapanks@gmail.com LINKEDIN: linkedin.com/in/malhotrapanks

WEBSITE: pankajmalhotra.com
LOCATION: Seattle, WA, United States

SUMMARY

About 10 years of experience in Software Development and 3+ years' experience leading a team of software engineers. Held positions with some of the most prestigious companies like, Amazon, Mozilla, Google, Hashicorp and BrowserStack in different capacities.

I lead a team of 6 software engineers working on a service called Health Event Automation and Telemetry(HEAT) at AWS Support. The portfolio of services I own publish messaging to AWS Customers during large scale events across AWS Services. During peak times, HEAT publishes messaging to up to 200k AWS Customers per minute. I enjoy solving problems related to cloud infrastructure and distributed systems, specialize in developing multi-regional, resilient services using serverless technologies.

WORK EXPERIENCE

JAN 2021-PRESENT

Software Dev Manager at AMAZON WEB SERVICES (AWS), Seattle, United States AWS Services/ Large Scale Operational Events/ Customer Notification Systems
Currently leading a team of Software Engineers working on services responsible for collecting service impact data during Large Scale Operational Events and notifying the customers about impacted services, regions and resources. I am responsible for efficiently driving team's Scrum ceremonies, conducting 1:1s with direct reports, managing performance, providing necessary support for career growth and finding opportunities for individuals to improve their skills. In addition, leading product initiatives, for defining a team's roadmap based on business needs. Actively participating in operational planning, monthly business reviews, quarterly planning, hiring initiatives. Raising the bar for operational hygiene of systems handling hundreds of thous-ands of accountslds per minute and delivering notifications in under 15 minutes of the detected impact to the service. Major contributions include achieving 75% reduction in Time To Notify(TTN) by increasing coverage of failure modes across AWS services. 45% yoy improvement in adoption of the product.

Nov 2019-Jan 2021

Software Dev Engineer II at AWS, Seattle, United States AWS Connect/ ACD/ Support Skill Queues, Routing, Chat Applications

Drove design and implementation for critical components of Slack Chat for AWS Support. Researched and implemented solution for core logic of routing chats to Support Engineers based on their skills, availability and support level of customer. Mentored other SDEs in the team. Helped break down the high level design into smaller components and tasks for estimations(Monte Carlo). Organized meetings with customers and stakeholders to get early feedback. Worked with a product manager to define milestones for the project and UX for improving the solution to deliver the best customer experience with 40% reduction in time for AWS Support case contacts.

DEC 2018-Nov 2019

Software Dev Engineer II at AWS, Cape Town, South Africa

Scheduling Algorithms/ Simulation Frameworks/ Prioritization and Routing

Worked on systems for routing and prioritization of AWS Support customer cases. Designed and implemented an improved prioritization algorithm for reducing the first contact time of AWS Support Cases by 60%. Coded a framework in Python for simulating customer case volume in different support queues in an ACD like system. Worked with product manager and customers for getting feedback on results from new algorithms and designed a strategy for phased rollout.

Software Dev Engineer I at AWS, Cape Town, South Africa

June 2017-Dec 2018 Serverless Architectures/ Multi-Leader(Active/Active), High Availability Systems

Designed and implemented serverless architecture for a highly available service operating in different geographic locations. Implemented active-active multi-leader mode for parallelising task executions in the service. The system helped move AWS Support from manual routing of AWS Support Cases to dynamic routing. It was a crucial building block for getting transparency in Support Operations and improving time for resolution, time for first contact and average starvation metric

from 8 days to 6 hours for AWS Support cases.

Software Development Engineer at BROWSERSTACK, Mumbai, India

SEPT 2016 -JUNE 2017 Infrastructure Operations/ Monitoring/ Logging and Web Services.

Developed and operated cross region data center services for ensuring High Availability and Uptime of applications. Day to day responsibilities included managing AWS Infrastructure for the engineering teams, full time oncall support, debugging network issues between AWS and data center infrastructure, creating virtual machines on hypervisors. Implemented time series monitoring using InfluxDB and Grafana. Designed and implemented software to enable remote debugging tools for mobile browsers. The new feature I implemented was a key revenue generator and also gave BrowserStack an advantage over competitors in mobile/device cloud space to sign-up new enterprise customers.

ENTREPRENEURSHIP AND VOLUNTEERING

Successfully grew a zero-waste and plastic-free health and wellness store in South Africa. Provided eco-friendly alternatives to everyday products, which helped customers create a cleaner, greener future.

Joined as a Director on board. I was responsible for overseeing all business operations and operated autonomously in all facets of business. Handled communication with customers and vendors, stock management, accounting, marketing and sales. Grew online store to 15k+ active customers with order volumes of reaching over 500 orders a month.

HELPED CREATE A COMMUNITY TO PROVIDE EDUCATION AND RESOURCES FOR HELPING PEOPLE MAKE INFORMED CHOICES ABOUT REDUCING WASTE AND LIVING SUSTAINABLY.

MANAGEMENT AND LEADERSHIP

EXPERIENCED IN COMMUNICATING WITH USERS, OTHER TECHNICAL TEAMS, AND SENIOR LEADERSHIP TO COLLECT REQUIREMENTS, DESCRIBE SOFTWARE PRODUCT FEATURES, TECHNICAL DESIGNS, AND PRODUCT STRATEGY.

EXPERIENCED IN RECRUITING, HIRING, MENTORING/COACHING AND MANAGING TEAMS OF SOFTWARE ENGINEERS TO IMPROVE THEIR SKILLS, AND MAKE THEM MORE EFFECTIVE, PRODUCT SOFTWARE ENGINEERS

EDUCATION

2012-2016 Bachelor's Computer Science and Engineering . IIIT Hyderabad, India.

INTERESTS

Web Engineering/Services, Automation, Distributed Systems, Serverless Architectures

SKILL SET

PROFICIENT: Python

Basic: Bash, GO, Ruby, Javascript

VERSION CONTROL: GIT, Mercurial

SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT: Agile, SCRUM/ KANBAN, Asana, Sprint Planning, Estimations,

Burndown Charts, Retrospectives, Deployments, Pipelines, Ticket Management

AWS SERVICES: S3, DynamoDB, Lambda, SNS, SQS, Elasticache/ Redis

Misc: Shopify, WooCommerce, Klaviyo, DNS based load balancing, Service Discovery, Health Monitoring

HA Proxy, NGINX, Websockets, TLS Terminators, MITM Proxy, Continuous Integration/Deployments, Travis, Jenkins, Selenium